don't you just love talking about
performance isn't it just so great to
just take something and make it better
make it faster hey what's up guys my
name is the chana welcome back to my C++
series we've been on a bit of a
performance trend lately last time we
talked about how we can actually use
multi-threading sed async all of that
stuff to make after you do multiple
things at the same time check out that
video if you haven't already because
it'll greatly help you speed up your
programs if you use it correctly
and in fact I know that a bunch of
questions did arise as a result of that
video I know you guys are interested in
that so don't worry we're gonna be
talking a lot more about this kind of
stuff in the future but today I thought
that we would actually just look at a
really simple example of what you can do
to make your strings faster when people
deal with strings I don't think they
realize just the kind of impact a string
has on the performance of your program a
lot of string operations in your program
formatting text you know logging stuff
getting into the right format using
substring that kind of stuff is easy to
overlook because you know I'm just
playing with a bunch of strings nor
playing with a bunch of strings is
actually bad and it's very slow and what
he's gonna talk about one of the things
that we can actually do this is very
very simple that will make our strings
and our string operations a lot faster
doesn't just feel amazing to be learning
all these new things but where do I
learn things other than programming I
hear you ask why Skillshare of course in
fact I'm pretty sure they have classes
on programming as well Skillshare is an
online learning community with thousands
of classes covering dozens of creative
and entrepreneurial skills and the best
part is that you get unlimited access to
all of these classes if you sign up for
a premium membership the more time I
spend programming the more I long to be
creative as someone who's not that great
at drawing I love how many illustration
classes there are on Skillshare that I
can check out they also have a bunch of
classes on things like cinematography
and what you can do to improve the
quality of your videos in fact I'm quite
impressed with just how many classes
they have to offer there are just so
many creative videos on there that I can
check out take a break from programming
skill show is offering you guys a two
month free trial if you sign up using
the link
in the description below and when you do
let me know what your favorite classes
are so that I can also check them out
and of course a huge thank you to
Skillshare for sponsoring this video
let's get back to strings I don't really
want to sit here today and just talk for
hours about why strings can be slow and
the technicalities behind all of that
I'd much rather just show you guys a
practical example of what you can do to
make them faster but if I had to sum up
one of the main issues with SCD string
and probably string formatting string
operations in general it's that they
allocate memory if you guys aren't
familiar with why memory allocation is
bad that's actually a really good topic
for a video by the way that I definitely
want to make but I do have a video about
the stack versus the heap definitely
check that out if you want more
information about just why allocating on
the heap is not the best thing to do
it's not that it's necessarily bad to
allocate on the heap it's inevitable in
a lot of cases in fact the way you can
avoid it you absolutely should because
it can slow down your program and sv
string and a lot of its functions love
to allocate and that's not ideal in fact
let me just show you exactly what I'm
talking about
so here we have a blank C++ program what
I'm gonna do is write some very simple
code I'm just going to make a string
called name I'm going to type in my full
name here and then I'm going to write a
function that's going to print name
right and what I'll do is I'll well I'll
take in a constitute a city string by
reference you know what I'm gonna
pretend to write a slow code here so
I've got a constant string reference so
there shouldn't be any copying of the
string going on here and then what I'll
do is I'll simply see out that name
string okay so here we go I'm gonna try
two different scenarios here first of
all I'm just gonna print that name just
by calling the function like this let's
see how many allocations we get from
this so how do we track these memory
allocations well a very simple way is
just to overload the new operator and
then this will just return malloc size
which is basically your basic memory
allocation and then I want to add some
additional things into here to make it a
little bit more obvious so I'll make a
you end 32t called s alec count which is
gonna be the number of allocations here
I'll just make this static for good
practice and then what
is s Alok count plus plus whenever we
allocate and then just for curiosity
I'll also print just how big that
allocation was so allocating size bias
okay cool so now all of our allocations
will flow through this new operator it
will count the amount of allocations we
actually have and also it will print
just how big that allocation is and what
I'll do at the very bottom here is also
just print that aleck count allocations
okay cool so there we go
let's run this program and see what
happens and as you can see here we've
allocated eight bytes of memory and
there hasn't been one heap allocation
now let's take a look at where that's
come from I'll just take a break point
over here and run the program again here
we go the breakpoint gets hit and you
can see that it's coming from this line
here when we actually create a string
and that causes a heap allocation if we
take a look at where it's coming from
it's coming from SV basic string of
course if we drill down a little bit we
can see that this in fact does allocate
memory okay but what if we do something
a little bit more simple what if we just
get rid of this string entirely and we
just copy and paste this kind of khonsu
our data right into the print name
function does that allocate memory yes I
know I write a comment below now I'm
gonna run this program and well as you
can see it does in fact allocate memory
so if we go back here this in fact does
allocate memory we're still taking in a
Const reference here of course but it
still needs to construct an sed string
for us and that construction allocates
memory let's look at a slightly more
involved example I guess this is really
really simple I'll go back to what I had
before and what I'll do here is I'll
actually just play around with the
string a little bit so maybe I want to
have the first name so I'll just do name
dot substring zero and three to get the
first three characters out and make its
own string I'll do the same for the last
name and then of course I'll start this
at index 4 with a length of 9 so now I
have the first name and the last name
maybe I just want to print the first
name I'll do that let's run this program
and see how many allocations we get and
you guys can write that in the comment
some counted yourselves so how many
allocations do you think we have here
the correct answer is three allocations
so already just with a few operations
we're already at three allocations and
you can imagine that things like this
might happen all the time throughout
your program and if you've got some kind
of real time running program like an app
or a game or something like that and
you're doing this kind of stuff every
frame then it can really pile up and it
can hurt your frame rate so is there
anything we can do to actually make this
better for us yes in fact there is
there's a very easy way that we can just
modify this existing code to reduce the
allocations to just one and what we'll
do by the end of this video is get rid
of all of these allocations we'll have
zero if we just look at this program
whenever you're optimizing you just want
to take a look at what it is you're
trying to do because in a lot of cases
just by kind of looking at the data you
can find ways to optimize it so for
example what am i doing with this first
name what do I want well really I just
want these three characters does
obtaining these three characters really
require me to make a substring I mean
what what that's doing is creating a
whole new string which is its own data
right so it's copying that data into
this first name variable right which is
a string but not only that if I don't
even copy the data if I just take this
obviously like that that's gonna
allocate in itself and you can see we
now have four allocations because what
it's doing is creating a whole new
string which can be mutated and has its
own memory but really what we want is
kind of a view into that string a view
you say that's exactly where strengths
view comes into play so essa' D string
view is a new class available in C++ 17
but to be honest I've been using stuff
like this way before C++ 17 what it is
is essentially just a pointer to
existing memory so in other words a
Const our pointer to an existing string
owned by someone else plus a size so
what that enables you to do is be like
okay I've got my name yawn charnok off I
can just go to that first I can have a
pointer to that first character and then
a size of three and then that would be
my substring or I can have a pointer to
the beginning of that string plus four
bytes which takes me to that beginning
of that surname of that last name and
then another nine for the size and then
that would be myself
so in other words what I'm doing is I'm
creating like a window a little view
into existing memory instead of having
to allocate a whole new string and make
a whole new string out of it using
substring I don't need any of that
because what I want is just a view a
window into an existing string which has
its own memory it's really simple to
write this kind of class by yourself so
way before say plus + 17 people were
doing stuff like this it's actually
quite common to do and the huge benefit
here is because I'm not creating my own
string I'm just kind of looking into an
existing string there is no memory
allocations it's extremely lightweight
to pass a string view around just by
value because all it is is a pointer and
a size so with that in mind let's
rewrite the current code that we have to
just get rid of substring altogether so
here we have these true sub strings that
we wrote of course I'm just gonna
rewrite them what I'll do is write STD
string view first name and then I can
use the constructor of string view to
specify this substring so in other words
I'm gonna go with name because that's
what the daughter is named dorsey string
that gives me a constant R pointer that
is owned by this name string and then
I'm going to specify a size of 3 and
then that that's that that's my first
name and then for the last name I'll do
the same thing except the difference
being I don't want to start at the
beginning of this string I actually want
to advance four bytes or four characters
forward so that I get through this
letter C here and then the length here
which is nine I'll just wrap this stuff
behind an ef-0 and then I'll write a
little else here so that we can test
both scenarios later and then in print
name of course I'm just gonna write
first-name now we have to modify this
function a little bit instead of just
taking in a constant a string now we'll
take in a strength you know need to pass
this by reference or anything like that
so this becomes just STD string view
name so now with this in mind let's run
this program and see how many
allocations we get and check this out we
just get a single allocation coming from
this original string of course
let's also copy and paste this and print
the last name here and then I'll just
run this program there we go we print
the first name and the last name and we
only have a single allocation how good
is that but we can do better than that
we can get rid of all the allocations
entirely and the way that we can do that
is by not using s it E string at all so
is a static string there's no real
reason for it to be an STD string we
could just make it a C string a conch a
pointer so now instead of this name dot
C string we get rid of that entirely the
code becomes just that and then if I do
run this program ah look at that isn't
that beautiful
zero allocations and I'll thing to note
here is that because I did change my
print name function from being a string
to a string view that means that if I
was to do something like I did before
where I just write print name and then
just an actual string here like this
this itself also have no allocation so
if I run this program you can see I get
zero allocations but if I go over here
and I change this to be an S City string
like this even though it is a constant
reference here I'll get rid of these two
because they're string views you can see
that just by printing name sure no I've
cost yet one allocation so even if
you're not doing any kind of substring
stuff you know all I want to do is have
this print name function then I can take
in a string view instead of a string
just by changing the signature of the
function like this and suddenly I've
gone from having one allocation to zero
allocations so in other words to
summarize so we have two cases here one
which uses strings and one which uses
string keys let's put them head-to-head
and see what the total difference is so
for this example I will revert this name
to being a string depends what the use
case kind of is but let's pretend that
this data isn't just being statically
typed like this in our C++ code maybe
it's coming in from a file or being
generated somehow in that case making it
a string would just be a more realistic
scenario that's all I'll change this
code back so that it actually works so
we'll add the dot C string here to get
the C string and I will also write two
versions of this function one which
doesn't use a city string view like this
and one which does and again what I'll
do is I'll put a little preprocessor if
and else here just to make that happen
what I'll do is write if string view so
that we use the string view way and I'll
do the same thing for here just to flip
these two around there we go so now we
have our if string view and the else
statement I'll come over here and I will
return our print names and I'll have
three different examples shown arrow
first name and last name so let's see
what this looks like so with string View
turned off I'm gonna run this program
and you can see we get four memory
allocations
whereas if I go ahead and define a
string of you just like that and I run
this we have just a single memory
allocation which of course is coming
from that original string creation so if
you guys want to take this further what
you can do is copy down the code that
I've written today and actually
benchmark and try and do it over like a
thousand four loop iterations try and
put it into your game loop or something
like that try and look into your own
existing projects and start replacing a
few of these strings with string views
and see what kind of performance impact
you have major speaking from experience
I know that if you look at pretty much
any game and you profile it and you
inspect it a sizable portion of that
will be due to string operations and a
lot of the times there's just not much
you can do but of course there's always
a little bit you can probably get away
with anyway I hope you guys enjoyed this
video if you did please hit the like
button let me know what you think about
all these kind of performance
optimization videos I love this kind of
stuff I love making this kind of stuff
so they'll definitely be more this in
the future as always don't forget to put
down any kind of requests you have for
people's videos in the comments below I
know my list is huge but I'm always
looking for new video ideas don't forget
to check out that to month free trial of
skill share by using the link in the
description below and I will see you
guys next time goodbye
[Music]